Guide to the Dennistoun Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dennistoun correspondence
1785-1855
OSB MSS 56
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.84
(4 boxes)
Letters from various correspondents addressed to Dennistoun or to his wife, Isabella. Many are of a social nature. Letters from William Carnegie Northesk and William Stirling Maxwell concern art collecting.
Dennistoun, James, 1803-1855
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JAMES DENNISTOUN (1803-1855)
James Dennistoun, the eldest son of James Dennistoun of Dumbartonshire, was born in 1803 and educated at the universities of Glasgow and Edinburgh, becoming a member of the Faculty of Advocates in 1824. His interest in art and antiquities, particularly the Italian masters, was strengthened during a tour on the Continent in 1825 and 1826.
After his father's death in 1834 he sold the family estate on the Clyde and purchased the farm of Dennistoun in Renfrewshire. In 1836 he left Scotland and spent the following 12 years primarily in Germany and Italy, pursuing research and collecting early Italian art, drawings and medieval antiquities. From 1847 on these were displayed in his Edinburgh home.
Dennistoun was a member of and contributor to the Maitland Club and the Bannatyne Club, editing several early texts for their publication series. The author of several works, he is perhaps best known for his Memoirs of the Duke of Urbino Illustrating the Arms Arts and Literature of Italy from 1440-1630 (1851), and Memoirs of Sir Robert Strange and Andrew Lumisden (1855). In 1853 he wrote an influential article for the Edinburgh Review criticizing the collecting policies of the National Gallery in London, and later that year appeared before the Select Committee on the National Gallery.
James Dennistoun died in Edinburgh on February 13, 1855. The greater portion of his collection was sold at Christie's & Manson's on June 14, 1855.
Scope and Contents
The Dennistoun Correspondence consists chiefly of letters addressed to James and Isabella Dennistoun. The letters span the dates 1785-1854, with a majority dating from between 1841 and 1854. The Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent; a small group of Other Papers is housed at the end of the collection.
The Correspondence contains primarily social notes, detailing plans for concert attendance, country outings, travel arrangements, and visits to and news of family members and friends. Letters by Sir Augustus Wollaston Franks and George Grove concern exhibition of some of Dennistoun's collection at the Adelphi Institute; letters by Alexander Christie discuss an auction of paintings. Art collecting and Italian painting are also the subjects of letters by William Carnegie, 8th Earl of Northesk and William Sterling Maxwell. Sir George Lewis's letters concern copy of Dennistoun's articles for the Edinburgh Review. In addition, there is a letter of introduction for Dennistoun's first Italian tour by Sir George Canning and a lecture pass signed by John Ruskin.
Other Papers includes occasional poems by James Dennistoun and James Murray of Elibank; one folder of invitations and musical programs; and miscellaneous bibliographical information.
Art -- Collectors and collecting; Dennistoun, Isabella Katharina Murray; Dennistoun, James, 1803-1855; Northesk, William Carnegie, Earl of, 1758-1831; Stirling Maxwell, William, 1818-1878
- Correspondence, Series I
  - "A"
    - Acheson, Mr. ALS to [James Dennistoun], Sheriff's Office, Glasgow, 1851 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Addison, Charles Greenstreet, d. 1866. ALS to James Dennistoun, Inner Temple, 1848 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Anderson, C.
      - ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Portland Place, 1841 Jan 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, Leamington, 1841 Apr 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Anderson, Francis. ALS to James Dennistoun, [n.p.] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Annison, Etienne to Mrs. Dennistoun, 1842 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Argyll, Anne Colquhoun (Cuninghame) Monteath Campbell, Duchess of, 1801-1874. 3 ALS to James Dennistoun, Rome and Inverary Castle, 1841-46 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Scope and Contents
      Social matters.
    - Argyll, George Douglas Campbell, 8th Duke of, 1823-1900. 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, Inverary Castle, 1847 Apr 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      On the 7th Duke's funeral.
    - Argyll, John Douglas Edward Henry Campbell, 7th Duke of, 1777-1847. 3 ALS to James Dennistoun, [v.p.], 1840-43 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Aytoun, Jane Emily (Wilson), d. 1859. AL to James Dennistoun, Gt. Stuart St., [1854] (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Cancels party because of illness of father (John Wilson).
  - "B"
    - Baillie, Margaret D. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Dumfries, 1842 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Beazly, C. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Arthursfield, 1841 Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Blackwood, John, 1818-1879. ALS to James Dennistoun, George St., 1847 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bolland, Louisa. ALS and AL to Mrs. Dennistoun, Cheltenham, 1841 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Gossip.
    - Bonar, Mrs. AL to Mrs. Dennistoun, Scholss Waasen, 1852 Jun (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Borthwick, Elizabeth D. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, George Square, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Boswell, Sir Alexander, Bart., 1775-1822. Signature: frank on letter cover to James Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1807 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bowyer, William Wentworth. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], 1847 Mar (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Boyle, Mary F. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Trusbanks, 1841 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Brewster, Sir David, 1781-1868. ALS to James Dennistoun, [n.p.], [1841 Feb 11] (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bruce, Katharine. LS to unnamed recipient, Clackmanan Tower, 1785 Apr 23 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Buchan, Agnes Graham (Smith) Erskine, Countess of, d. 1875. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], [1853 Feb 19] (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Buchan, Caroline Rose Stewart (Maxwell), Countess of, d. 1893. 4 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Melville St., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Buchan, Henry David Erskine, 25th Earl of, 1783-1857
      - 4 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, [v.p.], 1852-54 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Social exchanges.
      - ALS to James Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], [1853 Mar 26] (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Buchanan, Elizabeth Grace. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Arden, 1841 Sep 15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Burke, Sir John Bernard, 1814-1892. Letter (form) to James Dennistoun, Brompton, 1832 Oct 23 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Burroughs, L. 2 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, London and Naples, 1841 Jul 20, 1841 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Bury, Lady Charlotte (Campbell), 1775-1861. AL to James Dennistoun, Sr., Park Square, London, 1831 Jul 21 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Lady Charlotte Bury presents her compliments. With a printed page of prospectus.
  - "C"
    - Caithness, Frances Harriet (Leigh) Sinclair, Countess of, d. 1854. 2 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Rutland Square, 1852 Dec, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Callander, James Henry. ALS to James Dennistoun, Boquhan, Stirling, 1846 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      With 2 p. printed obituary of Mrs. Callander.
    - Campbell, A. Caroline. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Campbell, A. J. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Garscambe, 1841 Oct 7 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Campbell, Lady Emma, to James and Mrs. Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1854 Jul (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Campbell, Sir Ilay, Bart., 1734-1823. ALS to James Dennistoun, Sr., Edinburgh, 1798 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Campbell, J. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Craigie House, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Canning, George, 1770-1827. LS to Sir A. J. Foster, Foreign Office, 1825 Jun 18 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Chalmers, George, 1742-1825. ALS to James Dennistoun, Sr., Whitehall, 1798 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Christie, Alexander, 1807-1860. 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, London, 1848 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Sale of pictures.
    - Clark, Mary, Lady. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1831 [Jan 1] (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Cole, Robert. ALS to James Dennistoun, Warwick, 1847 Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Colombo, George to James Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1852 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Colquhoun, R. S.
      - AL (incomplete) and ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Glasgow and London, 1841, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - ALS to James Dennistoun, Wren's Hotel, 1842 Feb 13 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Combe, George, 1788-1858. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], 1843 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Constable, M. 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Charlotte Sq. and [n.p.], 1847 [Apr], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Coventry, A. 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], 1842, 1852 Jan (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Coventry, Jane. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Shamwell, 1841 Oct (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Crowe, Catherine, 1800-1876. 2 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Edinburgh and Mackeys Hotel, 1847, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "D"
    - Dennistoun, ----. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, [1842 Mar?] (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Dennistoun, Elizabeth. 6 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Greenlaw, 1841-42 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Dennistoun, James, 1803-1855
      - AL (incomplete draft, unsigned) to the Duchess of Argyll, Rome, 1824 Mar 8 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Edinburgh, 1834 Sep 3 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - ALS to J. G. Lockhart, Edinburgh, 1847 Mar 8 (Box 2, Folder 54)
        With two slip notes added.
      - ALS (draft) to Sir William Stirling- Maxwell, [n.p.], [ca. 1852] (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Dennistoun, M. R. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], [1841 Jul?] (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Dennistoun, Margaret. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Greenlaw, 1841 Dec 29 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Dewar, M. A. ALS to James Dennistoun, Bolsover Castle, 1846 Jul 28 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Dick, Jane Haig. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Dunlop, Alexander Colquhoun Stirling Murray, 1798-1870. 2 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Ballikinrain, 1841 Nov, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Dunlop, Ellen C. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Charlotte Sq., 1853 Jan 13 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Dundas, A. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Arniston (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Dundas, Elizabeth. 4 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Arniston, 1842 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Dundas, I. Hamilton. 2 ALS and AL (incomplete) to Mrs. Dennistoun, Paisley and Bowness, 1841 Jul 31, 1841 Sep (Box 2, Folder 64)
      Aunt to niece.
    - Durham, ----. 4 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, 1841-42 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Durham, Anne Isabella (Henderson), Lady, d. 1844
      - 6 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Fordel and Hill Street, 1840-42 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - ALS to James Dennistoun, Hill Street, 1841 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Durham, Margaret Anstruther (Murray). 2 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1842 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Durham, Sir Philip Charles Henderson Calderwood, 1763-1845. ALS to James Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1842 Feb 23 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - "E"
    - Eastlake, Sir Charles Lock, 1795-1865. ALS to James Dennistoun, Fitzroy Square, 1850 Nov 18 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Eastlake, Elizabeth (Rigby), Lady, 1809-1893. 3 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, St. Bernard's Crescent, 1848 Jul, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 71)
      Social engagements.
    - Elgin, James Bruce, 8th Earl of, 1811-1863. 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, Minto, 1846 Sep, Nov (Box 2, Folder 72)
      On his appointment to Canada.
    - Empson, W. to James Dennistoun, [n.p.], [1847?] Mar 20 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Erskine, Anna Calderwood Durham (Cunningham-Graham) Erskine, Baroness, d. 1886. 2 ALS and 1 AL (incomplete, unsigned) to Isabella Dennistoun, Largo, 1841-42 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Erskine, Louisa. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Craigforth House, 1841 Aug 10 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Erskine, Thomas, 1788-1870. ALS to James Dennistoun, Linlathen, 1842 Dec 17 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Ewing, J. A. 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, [n.p.], [n.y.] Feb (Box 2, Folder 77)
      On purchase of pictures in Italy.
  - "F"
    - Fergusson, C. Dalrymple. ALS to James Dennistoun, Kilkerran, 1841 Sep 23 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Findlay, John. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], 1842 Mar (Box 2, Folder 79)
      With verse enclosed, 2 p.
    - Finlay, George, 1799-1875. ALS to James Dennistoun, Southport, 1851 Jul 5 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Franks, Sir Augustus Wollaston, 1826-1897. 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, Adelphi, 1850 Feb, Mar (Box 2, Folder 81)
      Exhibition by the Society of Arts.
    - Fullerton, Letitia. ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Douglas' Hotel, 1841 Sep 8 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - "G"
    - Glencorse, John Inglis, Lord, 1810-1891. ALS to James Dennistoun, Abercrombie Place, 1852 Dec 28 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Gneist, Heinrich Rudolf Hermann Friedrich von, 1816-1895. ALS to James Dennistoun, London, 1851 Sep 24 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Gordon, Isabella. 6 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], 1842-53 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Graham, Charlotte. 6 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Largo, 1841-42 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Graham, Montagu William, 1807-1878. 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, London, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Grame, Cristina H. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Heriot Row, 1842 Apr 20 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Gray, Elizabeth Caroline H. 6 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Bolsover, 1839-47 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Grove, Sir George, 1820-1900. LS to James Dennistoun, Adelphi, 1850 Jun 24 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Grüner, L. G. ALS to James Dennistoun, Fitzroy Square, 1852 Jul 10 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - "H"
    - Hamilton, William Alexander Anthony Archibald Hamilton, 11th Duke of, 1811-1863. ALS to James Dennistoun, Hamilton Palace, 1842 Dec 10 (Box 3, Folder 92)
      With quotation, 1 p., on a portrait of Queen Mary.
    - Hay, Sir Adam, 7th Bart., 1795-1867. ALS to James Dennistoun, Kings Meadows, 1849 Jun 18 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Hay, Anne (Preston), Lady, d. 1862
      - ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1841 May (Box 3, Folder 94)
      - ALS to James Dennistoun, Rome, 1838 Oct 21 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Hope, John, 1794-1858. ALS to James Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], 1851 Feb 18 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Hudson, Octavius. ALS to James Dennistoun, Dept. of Science and Art, 1854 Mar 17 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Inglis, Sir Robert Harry, 2d Bart., 1786-1855. Signature: frank on envelope addressed to James Dennistoun, with embossed stamp, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - "I"
    - Ingram, Margaret. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Wingham, Kent, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - "J"
    - Jameson, Anna Brownell (Murphy), 1794-1860. ALS to James Dennistoun, Edinburgh, 1854 Nov 16 (Box 3, Folder 100)
      With Mrs. Jameson's calling card.
    - Jeannin, Mr. 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1840, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 101)
      Social gossip.
  - "K"
    - Kestner, A. 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, Rome, 1839 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - "L"
    - Laird, M. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - Lamont, Johann von, 1805-1879. ALS to James Dennistoun, Munich, 1837 Jan 9 (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Lewis, Sir George Cornewall, 2d Bart., 1806-1863. 6 ALS to James Dennistoun, Kent House and other places, 1853-54 (Box 3, Folder 105)
      Copy for the Edinburgh Review.
    - Lockhart, John Gibson, 1794-1854. 3 ALS to James Dennistoun, London, 1846-47 (Box 3, Folder 106)
      Contributions to Quarterly.
    - Longman, Thomas, 1804-1879. ALS to James Dennistoun, London, 1854 Nov 28 (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - Lumsden, Hugh. ALS to James Dennistoun, George Street, 1847 Mar 19 (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - Lyon, Blanche A. ALS to James Dennistoun, [London], 1850 May 1 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - "M"
    - Macdonald, Angus. ALS to James Dennistoun, Ratisbon, 1837 Feb 22 (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - Macfarlane, C. 6 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [v.p.], 1841-47 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Mackenzie, S. M., Lady. 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Delirin[?], 1841 (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - Mackenzie, Mr. AL to James Dennistoun, Abercromby Place, 1841 Sep 20 (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - McNeill, Lady Emma (Campbell), d. 1893. AL to Mr. and Mrs. Dennistoun, George Street, 1854 Jan (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - McNeill, Sir John, 1795-1883. Letter to Mr. and Mrs. Dennistoun, Queen Street, [1841] Apr (Box 3, Folder 115)
      A masquerade.
    - Millais, Euphemia Chalmers (Gray) Ruskin, Lady, 1826-1897. ANS to Isabella Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], [1853] Nov 15 (Box 3, Folder 116)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: John Ruskin
    - Minto, William Hugh Elliot-Murray- Kynynmound, 3d Earl of, 1814-1891. ALS to James Dennistoun, Minto, Hawick, 1854 Feb 23 (Box 3, Folder 117)
    - Monro, Alexander, 1773-1859. ALS to James Dennistoun, Craiglockhart, 1853 Oct 10 (Box 3, Folder 118)
    - Montrose, James Graham, 4th Duke of, 1755-1836. 1 ALS and 1 letter (in another hand) to James Dennistoun, Buchanan and London, 1827, 1832 (Box 3, Folder 119)
    - Montrose, James Graham, 5th Duke of, 1799-1874. ALS to James Dennistoun, London, [1832] Mar 16 (Box 3, Folder 120)
    - Mure, Catharine. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 121)
    - Mure, William, 1799-1860. 11 ALS to James Dennistoun, [v.p], 1841-54 (Box 3, Folder 122)
    - Murray, Isabella
      - 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Edinburgh and London, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 123)
        Mother to daughter.
      - ALS to Louisa Murray, London, [1841] Jul 23 (Box 3, Folder 124)
      - ALS to Thomas [Murray], Albion Hotel [London], 1841 Jul 20 (Box 3, Folder 125)
    - Murray, James Wolfe, the elder. ALS to James Dennistoun, Chateauloup, 1847 Nov 28 (Box 3, Folder 126)
      Regarding Sir Charles Adam
    - Murray, James Wolfe, the younger. 14 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [v.p.], 1839-42 (Box 3, Folder 127)
      Brother to sister.
    - Murray, Sir John Archibald Murray, Lord, 1779-1859. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Gt. Stuart St., n.d (Box 3, Folder 128)
    - Murray, Thomas A.L. 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Cadet Barracks, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 129)
    - Murray, William
      - 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Gt. Stuart St., 1847 Dec (Box 3, Folder 130)
      - 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, Gt. Stuart St., 1842 (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - "N"
    - Napier, Mark, 1798-1879
      - 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], [ca. 1850] (Box 3, Folder 132)
      - 7 ALS to James Dennistoun, [v.p.], [ca. 1830-50] (Box 3, Folder 133)
    - Nisbett, M. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Cornhill, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 134)
    - Northesk, Georgiana Maria (Elliot) Carnegie, Countess of, 1811-1874. 5 ALS to Mrs. Dennistoun, Longwood and Ethie, 1847-48 (Box 3, Folder 135)
    - Northesk, William Hopetoun Carnegie, 8th Earl of, 1794-1878
      - 5 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Edinburgh and London, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 136)
      - 6 ALS to James Dennistoun, London, Longwood, etc., 1847-53, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 137)
        Social, collections of pictures, etc.
  - "O"
    - O'Brien, Mary. 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Woolwich Common, 1841 May, Jun (Box 4, Folder 138)
    - Ogilvy, Gertrude. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Forth Street, 1853 Jan 15 (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - "P"
    - Pitcairn, Robert, 1793-1855. ALS to James Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1841 Oct (Box 4, Folder 140)
    - Popham, J. E. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Somerset St., 1841 Aug 31 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - "R"
    - Ramsay, William Ramsay, 1809-1850. 2 ALS to Isabella Denninstoun, Ainslie Place, 1842, 1848 (Box 4, Folder 142)
    - Rashleigh, C. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1853 Mar 14 (Box 4, Folder 143)
      Regarding birth of son.
    - Riddell, John, 1785-1862. 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, Edinburgh, 1836, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 144)
      Genealogical information.
    - Robertson Glasgow, J. R. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Rutland St., 1842 Feb 18 (Box 4, Folder 145)
    - Robison, Sir John, 1778-1843. Letter to Mr. and Mrs. Dennistoun, Randolph Crescent, [1842] Mar 9 (Box 4, Folder 146)
    - Ruskin, John, 1819-1900. Memorandum, holograph, signed: pass for Mr. and Mrs. Dennistoun, admittance to lecture, [Edinburgh], [1853] Nov 15 (Box 4, Folder 147)
      With covering note, signed Effie Ruskin.
  - "S"
    - Seton-Hay, Anna. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Seacliff, [ca. 1842] (Box 4, Folder 148)
    - Sharpe, Charles Kirkpatrick, 1781-1851
      - ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Princes St., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 149)
      - ALS to James Dennistoun, Princes St., [1839 or later] (Box 4, Folder 150)
    - Sinclair, Alexander
      - ALS to James Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 151)
      - ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, George St., 1855 Feb 28 (Box 4, Folder 152)
        Regarding family heraldry.
    - Sinclair, Catherine, 1800-1864
      - 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], 1853-54 (Box 4, Folder 153)
        Memoir of Sir John Sinclair; death of Lady Sinclair.
      - 7 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [Edinburgh], 1841-55 (Box 4, Folder 154)
        With 2 p., autograph, of jest. Social Engagements.
    - Sinclair, Sir John, Bart., 1754-1835. ALS to James Dennistoun, Rosedale House, 1826 Sep 5 (Box 4, Folder 155)
    - Skene, Georgiana, ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, n.p., 1841 Nov 17 (Box 4, Folder 156)
    - Smith, John. ALS to James Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1848 Jun 14 (Box 4, Folder 157)
    - Smollett, J. R. ALS to James Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1842 Apr 3 (Box 4, Folder 158)
    - Smyth, Susan. 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1841 (Box 4, Folder 159)
    - Steuart, Elizabeth Seton. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 160)
    - Steuart, Isabella Seton. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Allanton, 1841 May 11 (Box 4, Folder 161)
    - Stirling-Maxwell, Sir William, 9th Bart., 1818-1878. 2 ALS to James Dennistoun, Park St. and Dunblane, 1852, 1854 (Box 4, Folder 162)
    - Stott, H. 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Bath, [ca. 1842] (Box 4, Folder 163)
    - Strange, A. 3 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], [ca. 1842] (Box 4, Folder 164)
    - Strange, Isabella R. 3 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Laura Place and Southampton, 1839-48 (Box 4, Folder 165)
    - Strange, Isabella, the younger. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Upper Harley St., 1842 Apr 1 (Box 4, Folder 166)
      Asks if Swiss nurse may travel with the Dennistouns.
    - Strange, J. R. 3 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Southampton and Laura Place, 1839-48 (Box 4, Folder 167)
    - Strange, J. M. ALS to James Dennistoun, Tynan, 1847 Mar 11 (Box 4, Folder 168)
    - Strange, Louisa. 2 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, St. Leonards and [n.p.], 1841 Jan, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 169)
    - Stuart, Elizabeth Villiers. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Dromana, 1841 Jul 20 (Box 4, Folder 170)
      Regarding a good Swiss maid.
    - Sturnford, Joseph. ALS to James Dennistoun, Durham, 1842 Apr 18 (Box 4, Folder 171)
  - "T"
    - Thomas, E. Anstruther. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], [1841 or later] (Box 4, Folder 172)
      Regarding Mr. Durham's death.
    - Thornton, S. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Hastings, 1841 Oct 30 (Box 4, Folder 173)
    - Trotter, A. ALS to James Dennistoun, The Bush, 1852 Dec 8 (Box 4, Folder 174)
    - Trotter, Coutts, 1837-1887. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Forres St., 1841 Apr 9 (Box 4, Folder 175)
    - Trotter, Louisa
      - ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1841 Jan (Box 4, Folder 176)
      - 8 ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Forres St., 1841-42 (Box 4, Folder 177)
    - Turner, Isabella G. ALS to Isabella Dennistoun, Ladbroke Rectory, 1840 (Box 4, Folder 178)
  - "U"
    - Urquhart, Robert W. ALS to James Dennistoun, Sunderland, 1850 Oct 13 (Box 4, Folder 179)
  - "V"
    - Vière, la, Mme. AL to James Dennistoun, Lucca, 1838 May 21 (Box 4, Folder 180)
      With appended ALS by Mme la Vière.
  - "W"
    - Warburton, Eliot, 1810-1852. ALS to James Dennistoun, Melrose, 1852 May 2 (Box 4, Folder 181)
    - Wardle, A. ALS to James Dennistoun, [n.p.], 1852 Oct 19 (Box 4, Folder 182)
    - Watt, James, 1736-1819. ALS to James Dennistoun, Sr., Heathfield, 1816 May 18 (Box 4, Folder 183)